That's probably one of the meetings
where people cry the most. This is
Laurent, staff engineer and manager with
experience at Stripe, Airbnb, and
Instagram, and he shared the unspoken
rules he learned from these companies.
You mentioned the secrets that you
learned as a manager.
>> Every company does this differently and
has those like untold rules about
calibration. He also mentored me at
Instagram and helped me reach staff.
What would your advice be to someone
who's been stuck as a senior engineer
for a long time and they're trying to
make that jump to staff? The key is to
be able to identify problems and to then
be able to pitch and then solve them. I
think one mistake people make
consistently in their software
engineering career is to not
>> [music]
>> Here's the full episode.
What's the story behind you choosing to
join Airbnb and how were you thinking
about your career planning at the time?
At the time I'd been in the industry for
a few years. I'd worked at Apple and
Meta and decided that my thing was
developer productivity. That is like how
do you make people as productive as
possible, as effective uh as they can be
like software engineer, like how how can
they write code as as effectively as as
they can. And so I did that at Facebook
and we decided to move to San Francisco.
And I had to continue doing my job while
taking the bus an hour and a half each
way. And so like I immediately started a
job search and
I picked Airbnb for multiple reasons.
Like I I I love the people I interviewed
me there. Uh it was close by. I could
just like walk to the office.
Uh and I liked where they were at in
terms of like developer productivity and
what was remaining to do. It was they
were like
very early on. I joined as one of two
engineer on test infrastructure. So I
was just at like the beginning of like
when dev fraud was starting to be
multiple teams.
And I think that was like very exciting
moment to join.
So I understand at Airbnb eventually you
transitioned to management. I know you
started as an IC working on test
infrastructure team. And I'm curious,
why did you transition away from being
an IC?
So the setup was
um we had one manager was managing I
think like three or four different
teams.
And it was starting to get very very
busy because like when you're a manager
and you manage like
more than 15 people, then you don't have
much time to do anything else but the
people management tasks. And I felt like
it would be more effective
um if we took the team in if you had
like a more uh supportive structure for
the team and if we were able to like
spend more time in growing people in the
team because like the team was a lot of
people were like quite new
in in the industry and I think they
needed a lot of that support. And so I
started doing that as a tech lead. As we
grew the team
test infra was uh
I know like six, seven, eight people
after a year.
And then I was like the natural path
forward is for me
to become the manager of that team and
to be able to continue growing these
people, continue growing their career,
being very invested in their uh
in their success with more time than
what my manager could dedicate. So I I
went to him and I pitched it to him. I'm
like listen
that all those people they need like
more support. I can do that. I can try.
You can help me like be a manager and
and he said yes. It was uh very kind and
so like I started as a manager. Like
initially like I had only two reports
and then like the whole team reported to
me. It was a wonderful experience. It's
it's it's actually very unique like when
you become a manager of your peers, it
presents some interesting challenges. If
you were a peer to these people, would
there not be some I guess power dynamic
or some uncomfortable conversations in
making that transition? There were and
we're like very up front about it and I
will always remember this one guy
came to the first one-on-one
and he told me, I'm going to talk to you
about a situation.
And I want to know how you would react
and based on how you're going to answer
that, I'm going to know if you're a good
manager
or if I don't want to work with you. And
here's the situation.
>> [laughter]
>> You're at work, you open your laptop and
then you look at your email and you have
an email from uh recruiting saying
your employee missed the interview that
he was scheduled to do yesterday at 3:00
p.m. uh
You've got to talk to them about it. It
cannot happen again. What do you do?
And so like immediately I was like,
well, I'm going to ask you what you
think about it and about like what
happened and the facts and try to
understand like uh what actually
happened.
And he was like, okay, you passed.
Because the [laughter] way you fail this
is by just saying like you're grounded.
You
you did something wrong. Uh you didn't
show up to the interview because like
you don't know. Like it's possible that
they got the wrong name, that they sent
the email by mistake. And it's like
there's always two sides to a story and
it's very very important
uh if you want to be successful in
a job with other people that you hear
all the sides of the stories.
What percent of managers do you think
would fail that test?
When people approach management, uh
there is a type of people who think that
it's one size fits all. Like they
believe that there's like one strategy
to be a manager. Like I'm going to be a
tough manager or I'm going to be a micro
manager or I'm going to just be
hands-off
and just let people do whatever they
want. I think if you think in that way,
uh then you lack flexibility and a lot
of the situation it could work. Like say
if you if you're if you like
micro management, it will work if your
whole team is new grads. But it's not
going to work if your whole team are
like experienced engineer. So I think
it's about flexibility. It's about uh
knowing that there's not one way
to solve the problem and one way to like
solve every like coaching situation. You
have to try different techniques.
I I remember you mentioned to me before
that you were kind of bored at some
point and so I'm curious like
after living through that transition
what was
going from an IC to a manager in that
regard? Uh um yeah, I think I was bored
at multiple times
multiple points in my career. Boredom is
a very interesting signal to watch out
for. Like if you feel bored
in a job, something's not right.
And that means you've got to do
something about it. And so I
transitioned to manager because I felt
like that was how we could make the team
as performant as possible to like
deliver that big project that I was
leading as a tech lead.
And initially it was very intense. Like
as I transitioned to manager, you go
through all those trainings where you
learn about all the secrets about like
how uh you know like how we decide the
level of someone that comes in. How do
you do promotion? How do you do
performance? You all of those things.
Um
So that was very exciting and I was
curious about how all of those things
worked.
But
after that the next challenge was people
management.
How do you like establish a rapport with
the individual in the team? How do you
plan their career with them and how do
you like best represent their interests?
So there's like that rapport building
second phase. And then
while that was like well on on the way,
then I started to work on optimizing
because that's what I do. I always
optimize everything I do. And so like I
built a tool that looked at all of my
reports [snorts]
calendar and my calendar and tried to
defrag the calendar so that like it
would just like be uh
without the holes so they could have as
much focus time as possible. And and
everybody liked it. That was like really
impactful because then they could do
more
uh
software engineering and less
interruption. Um the other thing I done
after that is I decided to work on team
health because I think that people like
uh people are happy at work
perform well.
At least perform to the best of what
they can do, the best of their ability.
And in order to do that
I tried to set the goal of having the
highest team health score
in
uh the infrastructure group at Airbnb. I
was like, how am I going to do that?
I am going to just send a big form. I I
did a Google form with like all the
things we do as a team. Like uh we meet
uh for the stand-up on Tuesday at 9:00
a.m. Does that work for you? Is it
useful? Would you prefer another form?
Uh what do you get out of it? And so I I
asked about every process that we have.
Every way that we work together. It was
it was quite quite complicated. It was
like 20, 25 minutes to like fill this
out. I got the results. I was shocked.
It's like everybody thought the stand-up
was useful
for the other people.
>> [laughter]
>> And so we are spending so much time
doing that like very long stand-ups that
was useful for nobody.
And so we changed the format to like a
form that was useful for people.
And then we did that for every process
from like planning to how we work
together um even scheduling like when we
would like review code.
And it worked. Like then the team like
became a lot more
engaged
effective and started to be able to do a
lot by even spending less time working.
And so that's kind of what happened
because like once things were really
running well, I was at the time I was
getting married.
And I left for 3 weeks for my wedding.
I came back.
They had planned the whole next quarter
with like the algorithm that we decided
for doing the project planning.
And they had figured out how they were
going to work together, all the project
assignment.
And
I was like, what am I doing here? It's
like I'm getting bored. This is so easy.
And I have nothing to do.
And so then the next step I discussed
with my manager I I I got to M1 at that
point. It was to become a manager of
manager.
I was like, I don't think I'm ready for
that yet. I kind of want to do
a lot more coding because I I I like
writing code. I like the experience of
shipping something to production, seeing
seeing it work, seeing the graph move
and all those things. It's it's it's
very motivating.
So that I switched to being an IC after
that because I was bored. You mentioned
the secrets that you learned as a
manager and I'm curious if when you
switch back to being an IC, did those
make you a better IC and if so, how?
They did. Like all the secrets I've
learned
uh helped me become a better IC and
especially everything around
um
career progression
around framing your career, around the
performance review and the rating and
the promotion and things like this. Uh
but also everything about coaching and
having difficult conversations. So like
all those skills then became extremely
useful
uh and
I became like a lot better at it by by
by being a manager. And then I fostered
those skills and then that became
um
one of the main ways that I was able to
contribute through like leadership as an
IC. One thing that's interesting in in
your transition to management is I think
a lot of people they do it very
differently in that they ask their
manager or maybe their manager asks
them.
But you actually pitched your manager.
You actually had a here's the value for
you if I become a manager. And I'm I'm
curious
do you think that's the best way to to
transition to management? In general, I
think one mistake people make
consistently in their software
engineering career is to not be aligned
with their manager on what they want.
They are afraid of saying like, "Hey, I
want to get promoted next year or I want
to be an expert of this technology."
A lot of people just go through their
career quite passively and then at the
end of the year they just write down
what they've done and then present it to
the manager and then hope that they're
going to get what they want.
And I think that's sad because like life
is very short and I think it should be
an ongoing conversation and that makes
it much easier for the employee
and for the manager, which is why
I set up a very interesting metric when
I was a manager.
I call it the surprise factor. So we're
working in person it was at Airbnb.
And for the performance review, I went
into the room
and I asked them
before I delivered the performance
review which was like a paper with like
the rating, the promotion or promotion
write on a piece of paper, what is your
expected rating?
Are you going to get promoted? And
roughly like what what we're going to
talk about.
And
I do the same. We put the paper in the
middle on the table. We open the papers
at the same time.
If it matches, it's a pass.
If it doesn't match it's a fail.
Because like you want to minimize the
surprise. Like if you're a good manager
you don't want
uh people to have surprise at
performance review time. You don't want
them to be stressed out because people
who are like uncertain or feel like
um
at risk, they're not going to do their
best at work.
So I I I use this metric and I try to
drive it to like 100%. I it never was
exactly 100% but it came pretty close.
I I could see the value in that um
because I think a lot of people
obviously the negative surprises are
bad.
Um but also the positive surprises can
be bad as well. Yeah, the positive
surprises are bad. Like say if someone
does not expect doesn't think they're
doing well.
Okay. And then you think that you think
as a manager that they're doing very
well. You put them up for promotion but
you don't even talk to them about it.
Then that's going to be a very weird
positive experience and really what you
should have done is try to like coach
them before so they take more risk and
that they can accelerate their career.
Because if they if they are good and
they don't know, it's like that's
something that's coachable.
After transitioning to and from
management, I'm kind of curious your
thoughts on advising other people on
when they should move into management
and what the pros and cons are. What are
your thoughts on on that for ICs?
For me, the experience was invaluable.
So
nowadays I tell people
if you think you should you're you're
considering it, then just do it. You
need to have that experience because
it's a different job and you're going to
learn so much by being exposed to a
different set of skills, different
experience and you'll see if it's for
you or if it's not for you. Like worst
case scenario, it's not for you and
you do very poorly and then you learn
something about yourself.
But in every failure, there's a lot of
things that you can learn.
It's
um so my advice right now is to say like
you should
all try.
But first start with an intern.
See how it goes because it it's actually
an interesting experience to manage an
intern. It's not quite like being a
full-time
um
manager because you get very attached to
your little intern because you have like
one intern.
And in general your they're much earlier
in their career.
So you're very much directing
uh their work and so
it's uh not the same dynamic than say
like when you're managing like
high-level IC. And it's also only one
person that you manage, which gives a
huge sampling bias and so you see
management through the
lenses of like
that one intern that you have. That
means if you go to intern calibration,
that's probably one of the meetings
where people cry the most.
Why? Because they all everybody
everybody comes in with their intern
thinking because they they they've
really tried to like direct them and
coach them thinking they're doing so
well because they want their intern to
succeed. And they and everybody who goes
to this meeting tends to say like, "Oh,
my intern exceeds expectation, is doing
so well, they need a return offer." all
of this and they think their own
performance is going to be tied to that.
When that's wrong because like you can
be very successful as an intern manager
if your intern does not get a return
offer. If that was the right thing to
do, that was the right thing to do. So I
love I love that experience of like uh
being an intern manager. So at Airbnb I
ran um some of the calibrations for
intern interns with like all the intern
managers to try to make it uh less
scary.
To make it like to reduce that bias. You
mentioned a little bit about your
promotion to becoming uh a frontline
manager, going from M0 to M1. I'm kind
of curious if you look over your promos
cuz we talked about that surprise
metric. For yourself going through those
promos, were you surprised uh as you had
your promos happen or were you and your
manager on the same page? I know they
happened at different companies and
things but still.
That's a good question. I think most of
the time I was surprised.
And that's not a good sign because when
that happened and then like you're
surprised about like uh
something happening, that means you're
like you don't have a good read of the
situation. You that's a sign that you
need to understand the situation better
and you need to work on understanding
how the system works, what's being
valued at a company versus another one.
Um
I'm trying to think. I was never
surprised by like a promo but I was
surprised by like uh some ratings
sometimes.
Uh the one that surprised me the most
is
around that time. So I I was a I was an
IC
uh okay so IC four, I think. Oh, I don't
I think it depend on the company like
how you like the level below staff
basically.
So five for a lot of companies.
>> Yeah. So I was leading
that team, the test infrastructure team,
and I was really expecting that I would
get to staff.
At the end of the year, I was like, I'm
doing
great while delivering that project and
I'm going to transition into management
where I'm basically going to be
doing the same kind of thing but more
people oriented. What happened at that
performance review
is I got
I think I got a meets expectation
because it's like you change roles
in the middle of the cycle.
So therefore, you get an automatic meet
because you have not been in the new
role for a while.
It was really difficult because I was
like that's not right because like had I
stayed as an IC, I would probably have
gotten like the
the promotion to staff, but instead I
was like, okay, well, I'm just going to
make it work as an M0. I'm going to try
to get to M1 as quickly as possible.
That is the next challenge and that's
what I'm going to be doing. Ultimately,
all of this happened
probably because I was not having those
conversation with my manager as
explicitly as I should have been
about my career progression. I should
have said, what happens at the end of
the year
if I change role like two months before
the end of the year, what will the
performance rating be? Can you check?
And I should have had probably more open
conversation like this. That would have
avoided the surprise because it was
neither pleasant for me nor pleasant for
them. Did that reset your progress on
your career progression? Cuz you were
right about to get promoted. Every
company does this differently and has
those like untold rules about
calibration. Say like say if someone
transitions a role and they've been
there less than two and a half months in
the new role, it's automatic meet. Or a
new grad cannot get promoted in less
than X months because we never had one
that
we did that. So there are all of those
untold rules of calibration. What's
interesting about those rules is that
they are developed locally. So you have
like rules in like specific teams,
specific organization. Uh
and over time the organizations mature
and like those rules like change, get
codified, get communicated to the ICs.
If there was a rule I didn't agree with
or I didn't like, I challenged it
as a manager and I
disputed it. I was like, this is not
this is not
uh motivating because blah blah blah or
that's why I think. And ultimately,
I was always very aligned with the rules
at every company I worked at even if
that meant changing or editing some of
those things. Uh at Airbnb, I
then led a session for like
all the ICs in the in the org about like
what
really happens in calibration and I was
able to be very transparent
about what happened in that room.
And my bar was, if you teleport anybody
in that room at any point in time and
they see what's happening, they would be
proud of the work we're doing.
And they would not think that we're like
scheming or doing something that's like
uh objectively unfair or anything like
this. So for me it's like there needs to
be a value alignment for me to be able
to like do that job and that's that's
what's difficult because as a manager,
you represent the interest of the
company.
You have to put the company first before
your report. That's like an untold rule.
That's the way it is. So you there needs
to be very strong value alignment
between you
and the company.
You need to like be able to defend those
decisions because if you don't believe
them and you just lied, then it's going
to like make you
uh quite sad.
I mean,
if you have feelings.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah.
That's something I definitely remember
was uh extraordinary about working with
you is your
your willingness to dispute the status
quo.
And I feel like when people don't do
that, that's kind of how
bureaucracy kind of sets in. There's all
these rules and things that people are
following that they don't necessarily
believe.
Um
I'm kind of curious like you said you
were often successful in disputing these
rules and I think a lot of people
maybe you're frontline manager or an IC,
you don't feel agency in the ability to
change those rules or maybe it's too
much energy. Curious if you have any
tips on how to dispute these types of
things successfully.
I think it comes from my interest in
psychology and like the study of the
different kind of biases
that can uh
creep into those processes and how they
can negatively like
they can make us, you know, make
suboptimal decisions. So I think I
always start from that place of like
trying to understand from a
psychological standpoint like what is
objectively
uh something that is going to be
uh helpful
in evaluating employees. Cuz I think
that like I have bias, everybody has
bias and you want to minimize that when
you evaluate cuz you want the process to
be fair. Because the main main complaint
people would have about this process is
like, oh, it's unfair. I thought. So
there has to be
uh some set of like criteria and like
values that are um holding true. In
terms of how do you dispute it? How do
you go about it?
Uh don't do it in the room
necessarily because it's like as often
if like
uh it's not very effective to have big
disagreement with like
a lot of people at the same time or with
someone in front of a group that
completely changes the dynamic. It's
much much easier to start having those
conversations
one-on-one because otherwise people just
get very defensive because they think
their reputation is at stake in front of
the group
and they're going to get like so and
that's normal. That's like that's what
it means to be human. So gather
evidence,
make your case,
but take the time to understand why the
rules are there and why the person
people think that those rule had to be
there because like there's always a
story behind it.
And sometimes the story is like really
telling and really useful and like once
you hear the story, then you agree. And
sometimes it's just like
a wrong precedent that was set a long
time ago that's no longer valid. What
would you say in an example? Let's say
you're in your your org and then
a VP, someone five levels up says, we're
going to start counting the code changes
that people submit and they have to have
a minimum or else they get docked in
calibrations. It depends what it means
to be docked in calibration, but like
say if someone if I work at a company
and someone high up says like, oh, we
will automatically fire the people who
do like less than like the 10%
least coding contribution.
Um
I think it depends on like what the
company and and what it values. It may
it may be a useful metric. In general,
it's not
because people contribute in many
different ways and counting the line of
code or number of PR is a very poor
metric. So actually I was
uh
in that situation. Not as dramatic as
what you described, but like when I was
at Stripe, I was uh the tech lead for
developer productivity.
And we kept
um
wanting to have a measure of the output.
Like how productive are people?
It's like how do you know if an engineer
is productive? So you can ask them, it's
like, are you productive? You can count
how much they produce like the lines of
code.
Uh
and
there's many other things that you can
be doing. But it's hard. And so that's
what I set to do like when I when I
worked at at Stripe is like I was
unhappy with
uh people considering that as a
potential metric. And and I was not the
only one. Like pretty much everybody
uh disliked that metric even the people
who suggested it
because we all know it's it's a bad way
to evaluate
uh
engineering output. So instead what I've
done
is I looked at the journey of when you
make a change, when you go from your
branch to merging your change, there's a
whole journey. How long does it take?
What do you do in those phases? Like so
first you're thinking, then you're
writing your code, then you are sending
the code to CI, code review, going back
and forth, things like this. And so once
you start to look at this and you start
to look at the journey of like the
changes,
you'll notice that you get a lot more
interesting data than if you just look
at the number of like lines of code or
PR. You can see that say in an
organization, it takes them twice as
long to make a code change than in
another organization. And that gives you
a lot of lever
to like
go look into but like why does it take
them twice as long? How can you help
them? And that reframe the question
about like measuring the output
which should ultimately be
the manager assesses all the work that
someone is doing regardless of if it's
code or not to the question about like
how fast are they at like when they're
like
doing good, which is much more
objective.
And I'm not I'm not saying that if
you're fast at like shipping code, that
means you're very productive and that
people who are slow at shipping code are
not productive. I'm saying if someone is
slow at shipping code and everyone else
is fast,
then you have to look into why the
person is slow because that's very very
useful signal. Cuz like maybe they work
in a code base that's horrible. Maybe
they use like an
uh
a process that's very inefficient.
Before we leave your experience at
Airbnb, I'm kind of curious if anything
struck you about Airbnb's engineering
culture. I know prior to that you had
experience at Meta and Apple. So, um
what was kind of notable when you got to
Airbnb?
It was a company that it still is
uh led by designers.
So, it was harder to explain
why
the low-level infrastructure
thing about the code really matter. It
also has some upsides because I think
that by virtue of like coming from a
different trade, they add
uh different ideas that were also very
good. So, like one thing that they that
they've done at Airbnb that I thought
was like really amazing
is
we were
we were having a lot of incidents, a lot
of reliability problems. And they said,
"You know what is really good at solving
those things? People who are like
working in emergency situation,
firefighters.
People who are dealing with like actual
real disasters. So, we're going to hire
people from that background
who are like super good at like the
crisis management and we're going to
say, 'Now you're in charge of this
thing.'
And you're going to like change the way
we do the internet measurement. That was
genius because it's like
uh
it brought a lot of rigor
and interesting practices that then I
took at every job I went after that.
It's like it's it it's something that's
very important to to get right and I
think that that mindset of thinking
outside of the box like, "Hey, who's
good at doing that? Firefighter." Then
that worked.
You left Airbnb for Meta. It was just a
boomerang cuz you'd already been at
Meta. I'm curious what made you want to
leave Airbnb and go to Meta.
Well,
uh so like I said, I joined in 2016. It
was 2020. 4 years in. So, at that point
uh you were getting 4 years grant when
you work for like the those tech
companies. So, that means I had
um
a cliff of stock. And so, at that point
I started to like
uh my earning potential started to
decrease.
Uh
and that's generally what happened at
like at like 4 years unless you manage
to like score a lot of like stock
refreshers. So, I think part of it was
like financially motivated. Uh another
part was I
thought
because I worked on tested for I worked
on compute, I worked on databases, I
worked on all all around like different
infra teams that I wanted to be an infra
generalist.
I was wrong.
Uh but I thought I wanted to be.
And so, I looked for infra generalist
job and that's how I landed the job at
Instagram.
I got to be on call for
the 4th of July for Instagram. And
I remember I was trying to like go hang
out with my neighbors as we moved to a
new place and I kept getting paged and
kept going back home across the street
to like go and figure out like what what
didn't work. And I was like, "I am going
to do everything I can to make Instagram
as reliable as possible. And I know it's
possible because Facebook solved a lot
of those problems before and when I see
people work on the code at Instagram,
they don't use all of those tools
that's uh
that they use on the on the Facebook
side. And I know because I worked
there."
And so, I went and I pitched it.
I went to
uh my manager's manager.
I said, "Look,
we have all those incidents.
Uh there's all those tools that at
Facebook
they've been using for years and solve
all of those patterns of incidents. We
are not using any of those things. It is
time that we partner with them
and we unbottle of those tools so that
we can dramatically improve the
reliability of Instagram."
And then that's why I became
uh involved in that project.
How'd you find out who on the Facebook
side to talk to to get the buy-in for
such a large uh adoption of their tools?
So, basically they they paired me with
an IC who was working on the Facebook
side. Her name is Arianne.
And she was exceptional at getting this
buy-in on the Facebook side, bringing
the right people to the conversation.
And uh it's she's one of the most
remarkable tech lead I've seen and
worked with in my career.
Uh she basically did that.
I remember something interesting you
told me before is you wanted to be
mentored by her and you
made an explicit pitch to her actually.
I remember you were very you had a lot
of agency in actually going to her and
and setting it up. And I'm curious if
you could tell that story and you know,
what you might recommend for others who
want to set up mentorships. So, there's
several people that I met in my career
and then when I met them, I'm like
this person's able to be thoughtful, to
challenge me
and also seems to be
uh
very
it they would just work well with me.
They would be able to like make me
change my mind on topic and I would
relate to them. And so, they don't have
to be engineers. This person I met like
even outside of like software
engineering. Like my current coach for
example,
uh she has all of those qualities. And
so, when I met Arianne, I noticed that
like yeah, she had all of those
qualities. I'm like, "I really want to
work with this person because
she was very direct, very helpful,
thoughtful,
really excellent at like analyzing
problem and trying to explain like in
what ways I was thinking about the
problem the wrong way and like trying to
get me to change my mind." She got me to
change my mind about a lot of things.
And so
so so does my coach. I think that's like
that's that's
a measure for success is like are you
able to do you change your mind as a
result of coaching or you just do the
same thing you are doing before?
When you went to Stripe, I'm kind of
curious what were your first impressions
as an engineer there?
Everyone was I think that is like at
every job I had the impression like I I
often
have the impression that I work with
very bright people because that's the
case like at at like every job in this
in the Silicon Valley. Uh at Stripe
specifically,
um I like that everyone was very much
focused on making decisions based on
data. And there was like a big culture
around data, collecting data, analyzing
data, and making decision really
uh
using rigor
and science
rather than like
uh
you know, hunches and intuition.
Facebook also has that culture
uh of of like the experimentation. Uh
but Stripe has it to an even bigger
extent in my opinion.
And there is such a strong culture
around metrics. And I love that because
like I love metrics. I love like being
able to measure success and how uh
progress is made. So, I felt right at
home when I joined Stripe for that
reason.
You mentioned you were the TL of this um
dev infra team and eventually the scope
grew. It grew from 35 people to 140
people in this organization. And I kind
of want to learn more about the story as
it grew. So, I joined as like the tech
lead of build test and tooling. So, that
was a group of team
um that were doing
the build so let's say the build system,
Basil, the remote building, the code
management internal
and GitHub,
uh code review,
testing infrastructure,
testing data. So, that was that the the
group of team. And that that was great
for me because that's like the areas of
dev fraud I was like the most familiar
with. And so, initially I was like, "I
need to gain credibility."
Why? Because there's like those 35
engineers have been working here like
most of them a long time and I'm coming
as an outsider. I want to be able to
lead them and I want to be able to do a
good job.
So, I looked back at
when
I was in that situation. When I was in
one of those team and a new tech lead
joined in and think about like what is
it that they've done right and wrong.
And the thing that I came up with was
I think
you're doing it wrong if you use your
past experience all the time to justify
what to do. You're like, "Oh, it worked
at Facebook so it must work here."
Because it like uh belittled the people
and like their their experience.
You need to also not tell people what to
do because that's not how you build
uh
trust in the team. Like say imagine
you're Arianne and be like, "Oh, I've
never seen this thing work at any
company I worked at. So, we're going to
cancel this project."
That that doesn't work. So, I was like,
"I have a rule.
My rule is
I will not
tell people what to do. I will not
uh
reject a design outright.
I will never do that in my whole time.
And at Stripe, I never did that. So,
there's a couple time when I told people
what to do which was in situation of
like urgency when you're like solving an
incident and you're like, 'Yeah, you
have to do this. You have to do that.'
But otherwise, I managed to do all of my
work and all the influence and all the
change of direction
by asking questions.
Simply asking questions
and getting people to change their mind
themselves as opposed to just telling
them like, 'Hey, we have to do this or
we have to do that.'
So, that was my style coming in. That's
what I wanted to do. And I'm like, in
order to build credibility, I need to
need the engineers to know me, to know
my style. So, I'm going to embed in the
different teams. So, I embedded in the
teams.
And started to work with the people on
like uh say I would embed in a team to
go work on a specific project for like a
month. Just to see what the rhythm is
like, how people work together. And so,
after a year, I'd met everyone
in person multiple times. I had like
embedded in like pretty much
all the different parts of the the
group. And I felt like I had a good
grasp.
And then I was like,
"But I know less than every individual
person about their domain."
And that's what leadership is. Like,
unfortunately, like when you are like
say in charge of like a large group, you
by nature know less than every person
about their own domain. And you have to
accept that. And it's very very
different than what happens say when
you're the tech lead of a team, where
you're the person who knows the most.
So, there's that that transition.
And I was able to navigate that
transition by just changing my mindset
and thinking,
"People are experts. I'm supposed to
guide. I'm supposed to ask questions.
And that's how we're going to get there.
And
it's going to work because I know I
I have a good hunch for like how to
solve developer productivity problem. I
worked on that
many many years.
And
just naturally, I always think about
like how to do things better. So, I will
just ask good question, and that's going
to work out." And it did.
Um
after that, the model shifted a little
bit.
Um when the org was like about
40 50 people,
uh I shifted to a mode of operation
where I would be deployed to go work on
something for like
say
two to eight weeks.
And then go that would not necessarily
be with a team. It could be with like a
group of team, could be with like one or
two individual, it could be with like
teams outside of DevProd to just go
solve problems. And that's basically the
mode of operation that I really really
enjoyed. Because then
you just get to like bootstrap thing get
things started, get things in motion,
motivate,
and then start the execution, and then
after that uh making it sustainable so
that like it can operate without you.
And that's something that's very
important for me is that like at every
of those assignments, I always think
about sustainability first. What happens
if I want to go on vacation
next week?
Will they have to call me? Will they
have to ask me anything?
I want this to never be the case. I want
everything to be like documented,
automated in such way that like
sustainability is not a problem.
I never want to be that guy who knows
all the secrets
about like the code base. And then
you're supposed to ask like, "Hey, how
do you change this style?" That's not
how it should be.
And that's one thing I learned as a
manager.
On that topic of of scaling yourself, I
mean, if the group grew to so many
people, I'm curious, do you have any
tips on how you scaled yourself across
such a large group of engineers? Um I
have a lot of tips about that. So, what
what one very important one is in terms
of uh the own expectation about what you
can do. When you're leading a group of
70 engineers, you cannot possibly know
what everyone's working on
at any point in time.
You have rough idea.
And you have to be ready to like have
your contacts in all the different
places to be able to gather information
quickly. But imagine you're in a
leadership meeting, and then someone
asks you like, "Hey, what's the progress
on this project?" It is possible that
you're not going to know. Because
there's so many projects across so many
engineers. And you have to be okay with
saying like, "I don't know. I will be
checking on this and get back to you by
that date."
And it's okay to say I don't know um
even if it's uncomfortable because you
think that you're like appear not
competent by saying I don't know. But
that's quite the opposite.
It's much better to say I don't know
than to say something wrong. Because if
you say something wrong,
uh in a lot of the culture for tech
companies, it's the end of your career.
Like, if you claim with confidence
something that is wrong, you're going to
lose all the respects from your
co-workers who are not going to be able
to rely on your word moving forward. And
it's a massive massive problem.
And so, I've seen like
uh it's not the case for all the
industries. That's interesting, right?
It's like it's it's a case for for
software engineering.
And
so, you have to say that, and then you
have to scale yourself. So, that means
you can't know everyone in great detail.
You can't like meet with everyone every
week. That's absolutely like impossible.
So, then I think you have to switch to a
model for what worked for me was
office hours.
You set a block and be like, "You can
book time with me to chat, and you need
to have enough office hours so people
can always chat with you like the week
off." And what else worked for me? I
work with people in Europe, so I shifted
my work schedule. I started my work at
like 5:30 a.m.
up to noon.
And this way I had like overlap with the
people in Europe.
And then overlap with the people in the
United States. But like half of the
group was in Europe. So, I think it was
important in order to like really get to
know them, motivate them, and influence
their work to have some face time, to be
able to like communicate with them.
You've done so much coaching throughout
your career. And you said that was a big
part of your experience at Stripe as
well. Is some of the topics on how to
coach well? And And one thing that I
want to go over is
what are some of the things that you see
people who are coaching software
engineers or people in tech,
uh what are they commonly getting wrong?
Uh um
when you hear someone say,
"Oh, I'm hands-off."
Or
"I like to tell people what to do and to
give a lot of details." Or "I just like
to give little hints."
Basically, that's just one way to coach.
And the reality is when you're coaching
people, you have to adapt to your
audience, and you have to change your
style. And if you use your one way that
worked with some people, it may not work
with everybody, and it's going to give
you surprisingly bad results. And I
experienced that very early on in my
career, which was like
uh
very helpful. It's I joined
uh when I joined Facebook in 2014.
I became an onboarding buddy. And I was
asked to help uh
several people through the boot camp at
Facebook. So, the first few weeks to
know like to teach them like how to use
the tools and how to like be an engineer
at Facebook, basically.
And three out of four of my mentees
were doing well. Were doing exactly like
what what you typically see. And then
the last one, no progress.
And so, the people in charge of the
program were starting to get a little
nervous.
And you know, we were having those
meetings every week when we were
reporting the progress of like the the
people. And be like, "Okay, we're going
to have to change the technique." And
then
the person leading that program,
uh I think it was Scott Renfro. He took
me aside.
And he said, "Hey, listen. Maybe you
should look into this thing called
situational leadership."
I'm like, "Okay, I'm going to look it
up." And situational leadership is a
very interesting model, and that
unlocked that situation with with that
individual, and turned them into
like the most effective of the four
who I was in charge of. And so, the way
it works is when someone's learning new
skills, they progress along
multiple axis. It's not just a mastery
of like learning the skill, but there's
also the motivation.
And that's very interesting because
psychologically, like if someone's
trying to like learn a new skill, in
general, they're like quite excited.
But with like low mastery of the skill.
And then as their mastery grows,
they start to realize that they don't
know.
And their mastery grows,
and they still think that they don't
know, and they're like not confident.
And over time, both of those like climb
up and to the right. And so, this
divides
the learning into four phases,
which are like those things, the
situational leadership. And depending on
where someone's at,
you do the approach very differently.
And that applies to every situation. It
could be like my mom trying to do
something on an iPhone, my daughter
trying to figure out a game controller,
or a software engineer trying to figure
out what technology to use for their
project. You have to have
that internal assessment of like where
am I on that skill that they're trying
to do?
Where are they?
And what approach should I take?
And so, the idea is that like if
someone's learning at the beginning, you
have to be very directing. You have to
say, "Oh, you have to do this. You have
to do that." And so that they can learn
the rope and like learn learn to do the
different steps.
As someone
progresses, you have to switch to being
like more uh selling the idea,
encouraging, say, "Oh, yeah, you're
going to be able to do it." And
help them with like the the difficult
decision. Maybe like take the high-level
decision-making, but letting them do
like the individual task.
And then as they progress, you have to
empower them
to like be able to like make those
decisions themselves. You have to just
switch to being supporting.
And finally, you have to be delegating.
That means like once they know how to do
the thing, you have to know to stay out
of the way. And I think this is whole
uh
dance that happens for like every skill
is very, very important to understand.
Because if you don't understand that,
and say if like your approach is you're
going to just tell people like
good work, keep going. Then you're going
to be doing just the supporting ones, so
you're only going to be able to catch
the people who are in that window and
and be effective for them. Everybody
else is going to be counterproductive to
do that. So you have to understand. And
so like after doing it for like so many
years, it becomes natural and like you
don't even think about it. And this is
like obvious that's like uh
if my mom calls me
at 4:00 a.m.
and she says my phone is reading
notification aloud, what do I do?
I'm not going to start to explain to her
all the systems. I'm going to be like
share your screen, click this button,
click this button, click this button,
done.
And I'm not going to go into the detail
about anything.
And it's not It is like it's
situational, right? It's like it's at
4:00 a.m. she's tired. Uh
it's it's it's like a situation where
you have to be directing.
And like if instead I'd be like
Mom, you're so good at the iPhone. You
know all the settings. Good work, keep
trying. Do you think she's going to be
able to be doing it? No, she's not.
She's she's going to be pissed off like
if if I do that. And if I say like
oh, bye-bye. I know you can do it.
You've proven times and times again that
you can do it. That would be delegating.
That would not work.
And then if it's the Yeah, so like it
for every situation like this
you can apply that framework. And it's
very interesting because like people
make mistakes with coaching. They think
that they know the way. They find the
technique that works, and they pick one
of those four, and they forget the rest.
So yeah, I'm curious in the in the
specific example with that one boot
camper who was not succeeding, where
were they in the lesson? Where did you
go wrong in the coaching, and how did
you fix it?
I
went wrong
in
thinking that everybody who starts is in
the first bucket, which is like highly
motivated, highly motivated, low skills.
And we're like you will start to be like
directive and be like, "Okay, follow
this page. Do all the steps to learn
those tools."
This person
had spent a lot of time going and
studying all those documentation and
everything like that. Has already
internalized a lot of the things and
realized that he didn't know that much.
And that he was at the point where like
the motivation was low.
The knowledge was higher than the other
people. But because I was coming and
directing
it was like interrupting their learning,
and they were like unable to actually
like perform in that way. So like when I
was like, "Okay, uh
what have you done?" And then they
explained that they've read all those
things, and I switched to being like
more supporting and like actually giving
like way less advice.
Um about what to do, then they started
to perform. And that felt like magic,
and I was like, "What's happening?"
It's like
w- why w- how?
Then I I've I've learned this, and then
I've applied it to so many situations,
and it's very useful skill
even as a parent.
Cuz like, you know, kids are always
learning things, and they're always at
different point in the learning scale.
I remember when we were working
together, you actually coached me out of
getting stuck as a IC5 or senior
engineer. I remember you said something
to me. You said, "Actually, the promo
from senior to staff is actually harder
than the one from staff to senior staff
because of some specific reasons." And
I'm curious if you could share those
reasons, and also some advice for people
to get unstuck from that senior
promotion.
The senior to staff promotion, it's
about like a big a big mindset shift
where
you
have to be
uh
completely independently picking
problem
solving those problems end to end,
explaining how you solve them, and then
uh documenting like what you've done.
It's like the whole cycle
of finding problem to solve, pitching
problem, solving problem
you have to be able to do that to be a
staff engineer.
And that's hard.
It takes And like when you're a senior
staff, you're just doing the same thing,
but with problems that are like higher
uh scope. And like when you're like
principal engineer, I think it's the
same thing, but like higher and higher
scope. That's kind of like how it goes.
But when you are a senior engineer,
you're in general like working on other
people's problem that they've
identified. And then they ask you to
design a solution, and then you solve
it. But like you're not autonomous on
like the whole cycle
of the problem discovery, choosing what
you get to work on. I think that's
really what's what's uh
the distinction.
What would your advice be to someone
who's been stuck at as a senior engineer
for a long time, and they're trying to
make that jump to staff?
The key is to be able to identify
problems and to then be able to pitch
and then solve them, and to identify
bigger problem than the one you
currently know about. And the way you
find out about problems
at least the way I do is uh by
channeling my inner frustration.
Which means I do something
and I'm thinking
oh
looks like I had to type all those
things on the keyboard and open this
window and all all
It's like it took it took me a while. I
don't want to do that again. I want to
do better. And so that that works really
well for like developer productivity.
Like I can do anything
and I can
be able to find all of the friction
all of the little parts that are uh not
ideal. Oh, and that's one thing that
Stripe does extremely well.
And
uh
that they managed to like
institutionalize for the culture in this
idea of a friction log.
You go through the flow of your product,
whatever you're working on.
And
you take pictures of the different
steps, and you describe like what you're
doing.
And you analyze the friction. Every
single step that you have to do, why do
you have to do it? Why did it have to be
a new window? Why did it have a loading
screen? How long did it spend all those
things? And so
I've gotten really good at that cuz I
practiced a lot at
at Stripe where I would just
go and make a code change, and I could
find 50 or 60 different things that
could be done differently. And then
after that, you identify like
the families of problem, we rank them,
and then you go and solve them. So it's
like
the same for any role. You just use your
product.
You
really use it like from first principle,
take pictures of your experience, and
channel your inner frustration. Try to
think
if I was very, very tired, and I was
going to do these things
where would I fail? Where would I get
stuck? Like where
uh
where would like I drop off, and then
try to remove all of those frictions.
And that helps you identify like the
biggest opportunities for impact.
That's that's how I see it. I think
that's like a very effective way to
to do it. Like for example, imagine you
go and you do business travel.
And you're doing it like 20 times in a
year. I think it's useful every time
to learn something new, refine your
process, and get better at it so that
like on the 20th travel, you're just
like extremely effective at it. I guess
that's like the staff engineer mindset.
>> [laughter]
>> Is there a book that had the biggest
impact on your career?
When I started being a manager I had to
have uh
all those
conversations that were not very easy
with the people in in my team. And in
order to
be effective at it, to build trust, and
to be able to
um
effectively motivate and coach
I found that Radical Candor was the book
that really gave me that. It's written
by Kim Scott who used to help managers
at Apple like as part of their training
to figure out like how to be a good
manager.
And she talks about
how you build trust in those
relationships, and like how do you view
the manager employee relationship
in
and she has a lot of very good points
that I have not seen mentioned in other
books, and some ideas
that like quite frankly, a a lot of like
companies and season managers are
missing. So it's it's a great book. She
also has like uh
TED Talk on YouTube where she talks
about it, and I think it's
it in my opinion it's been like one of
the most influential thing I read.
Last question for you is if you could go
back in time to when you just entered
the industry and give yourself some
advice
what would you say?
It's moving even faster than you think.
So you have to always stay on top of it
because software engineering is evolving
so much. So like when I entered the
industry Google was asking people
how many golf ball can you put in a 747?
And that was like the interview,
literally. There was like a book called
Cracking the Coding Interview where they
tell you about all those problems that
are like weird, and that you have to
like estimate, and that's how you apply.
Nowadays, in 2025 when you interview,
you're like recorded by a camera. Your
screen is being recorded to make sure
you're not using the AI. And you have to
explain what you're doing, and it has to
be about coding, and it's very, very
like
technical.
Like So everything changes so fast. The
whole career changes. Being a software
engineer today is not at all what being
a software engineer in 2012 was. It
doesn't take the same skills.
It doesn't take
the same
um
It's hard to stay on top of everything.
You have you've got to keep reading like
the tech news. I really recommend
reading Hacker News if you don't.
There's a a special version that like
you can rank over the last week which
one are the most popular. That's what I
use. It's hn.algolia.dev,
I think. It's it's really effective.
Like I read everything that's been
popular in the last week and I've done
that my whole career and that's how you
stay on top of it and it moves so fast.
It is not the same to be a software
engineer now than it was 10 years ago or
20 years ago and I know that in 5 years
it will be very very different.
Awesome. Well, thank you for your time,
Ron. I really appreciate it. I'll I'll
put all the links in the show notes, the
stuff that you said.
Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on,
too, please let me know. I feel like
sourcing very senior ICs, there's no
well-studied list out there on Google
that I can just search this up. So, if
there's someone in your org or at your
company who you really look up to and
you want to hear their career story, let
me know and I'll reach out to them.